Oh Vasudeva suitum daivam come such are
no drama Dunham's dave aqui para maana
and krishna monday an announcement i see
that many of you i think all over all of
you taking off your shoes you know that
it's not necessary so if you i know some
feel uncomfortable if they don't take up
the shoes but if you are comfortable
with it then you can come in with shoes
just accept this prayer area you can sit
there with shoes also that's all right
so we are studying the second chapter of
the bhagavad-gita where shri krishna is
giving the central teaching about the
Atman about the self what we really are
this is maybe this one thing that you
can take away from the bhagavad-gita it
would be this one the teaching about the
Atman that we are this immortal
spiritual being that old saying we think
we are human beings in search of
spiritual experience but the truth is
that we are spiritual beings having a
human experience so what have you
learned so far
Shri Krishna has said verse 11 12 13
that the Atman is immortal not subject
to birth and death one very big teaching
the body dies the Atman you the self
Atman does not die then the sixteenth
verse even more stunning the Atman alone
is real the world of appearances this
world is a world of appearances
including the body and even the mind
they are not independent realities I
will not explain we have gone through it
in detail
not being independent realities their
reality depending on the Earthmen this
dependent reality another term for that
is falsity or myth theater so that was
that's what we saw in the sixteenth
verse the Atman is not only eternal it
is the only reality and the non Atman
did non self body mind and the rest of
the world they are appearances in the
Atman then 17:17 twerks we saw the Atman
is if it's the only reality then
whatever you experience must be the
ultimate so it is all pervading the word
used was serve a minimum everything that
you experience is pervaded by the Atman
contrary to what we normally think Atman
means the self come on it the Atman
means the self but we normally think
that there is something which is the
non-self that is other than me here we
are taught that whatever you regard as
other than you is in a deep sense
nothing but you so the Atman pervades
everything the self pervades the
not-self that's the third thing we
learnt that was in verse number 17
another these are all each of them can
take several lectures to you know to
probe the word assimilating and they are
all counter intuitive the eighteenth
verse tells us the Atman is not an
object it's not an object a premier
premier means not an object of knowledge
it's not something that you see hear
smell taste touch it's not something
that you infer it's not something that
is an object of scientific enquiry or
religious belief rather it is the pure
subject it is not the object of
knowledge rather it is a subject it is
not something that is known rather it is
the nor nor yes and which has many
ramifications when you look at it that
way then it first
of all it points out clearly what the
Atman is or where it is where it means
within courts and why we cannot see it
as an object then then the next verse
nineteen twenties not an inn not a doer
of actions nor is it the experiencer of
the results of actions in sanskrit occur
table hook that's not the kurta the doer
agent of action bhakta means the
experiencer of the results of actions so
the Atman in itself is free of the law
of karma free of karma cause and effect
it's beyond causality so these are all
extraordinary claims and all
counterintuitive it's very its natural
for us to think that I have been born
and I shall die it seems to be the
fundamental truth
the first thing Krishna said that no
you're not born nor shall you die you
are immortal then the next thing which
seems common to us is that here is
earlier I don't know what I am but the
world here is very real just the
opposite you are the reality and the
world is your appearance again
counterintuitive I think intuitively I
think I am here small a tiny part in of
a tiny speck in a vast universe so
limited in space tiny just here so
limited in time born and dying
neither limited in time not limited in
space counterintuitive that you are the
vast you are unlimited all-pervading and
then again when it says that you are not
an object of knowledge we have almost
instinctive urge to objectify very
understandable because everything that
we have known in our lives and anybody
has known in the life that there has
been an object of knowledge either it's
something that you've seen or her
or smelt or taste or touch or it's
something that you have thought off
remembered conceived speculated about
proved believed they're all objects to
consciousness when you get what they're
talking about it's direct it's it's very
intuitive it it's it's very very
blindingly obvious but until that time
we tend to keep keep making this mistake
whatever we are taught we think it's
some object which you are talking about
and in fact I mentioned that once we
begin to understand it's not an object
our reaction is it doesn't exist then
because everything that we have
experienced is existing is an object so
we go into nihilism or emptiness junetta
no the Atman does exist it is you and
it's not an object it's not an object
but look at our language even the word
it is an object word it it's that then
the next one occur table hook now what
could be more natural than thinking of
yourself as the doer of actions and we
think of ourselves as I enjoy I suffer I
am the enjoyer and the sufferer and he
says no no you are not the doer nor are
you the enjoyer or the sufferer then
next 20th words
so please chant up to me no jyoti Realty
baka dodge it Naja you team Ryota vaca
dodge it now um who table Vita wanna
booyah now iam Buddha Amitabha Naboo Oh
Joe Natasha SWAT Oh Emperor no ah Johnny
thr SWAT Oh Emperor no na hanyate
hanyamane sarire a na hanyate hanyamane
sarire so the self Atman remember
whenever we're talking about the self
it means you you might because the mind
is very tricky
yeah I might end up saying yes I
understand myself is wonderful but I
have some problems self means you it the
self is not born and it does not die at
any time
it does not again come into existence by
being born it the self is worthless
constant eternal and ancient it is not
slain with the body is slain so it is
the meaning of the verse as we go a
little deeper into this it becomes very
interesting before I forget let me tell
you that I was studying my copy of the
chancre of Russia the commentary by
Shankar Acharya so I found a note there
in my handwriting so I don't know where
I got it from it's not Shankara said
that it says you see in philosophy at
least in Indian philosophy Pune octi is
a dosha
pune rook tea means the repetition if
you say the same thing over and over
again it's considered a fault it should
not repeat something now here it seems
to be a clear case of repetition it's
not born it does not die one he says the
same thing it's not that it was existing
and he died and then again came into
existence
that means damn being born and dying
then again it says it is not born a job
unborn
it is eternal does not die it is not
killed and when the body dies it does
not die so he seems to be a case of
three times repetition once it is said
neither born not dying second again and
third again so the note which I found it
said that it's not actually a case of
repetition it is
protego hey - nigga mana what does it
mean in logic Indian logic the way an
argument is framed the way an argument
is framed is in a syllogism
okay now have to explain what a
syllogism ish those who are stood in
students of logic or philosophy you know
that so the classic one in aristotle and
logic when you say all men are mortal
the classic example Socrates is a man
therefore Socrates is mortal
so three statements that two are given
to you and third one you derive from it
the first two are all men are mortal
second one Socrates is a man and
therefore what do you derive from this
Socrates must be martyred so this is
called a syllogism the form of the
argument the different forms of argument
now this very thing in Indian philosophy
the eye a logic this very thing is done
in not in three parts two premise major
premise minor premise and the conclusion
one two three Socrates all men are
mortal Socrates is a man and Socrates is
mortal but in five parts
so in Naya philosophy in India the
syllogism has five parts the the first
one is called pratigya particular at
which is to be proved let me give an
example it'll make things clearer the
classic example those have studied
Indian philosophy knew you know that the
classic example is
there is fire on the hill because there
is smoke so you can see smoke you don't
see the fire you see the smoke it's not
a hill here supposes
there's a fire on on on a skyscraper and
the fire department you know it clanging
and the sirens blaring the fire
department fire trucks go rushing by
they haven't seen the fire yet but they
see the smoke now by seeing as you see
in smoke that is direct perception and
you are inferring inferring fire you
know there is fire how do you know did
you see it no what did you see smoke and
you know that there is a connection
between smoke and fire with putting
these two together the seeing the smoke
and the knowledge of smoke and fire go
together you you infer that there is
fire and then you go out to put it so
the classic example in Indian philosophy
is pervert oh one Neema and room art
there is fire on the hill because there
is smoke because I see smoke so the
first sentence is what do you want to
prove I want to prove that there is fire
on the hill that is called the first and
that is called hey 2i that's called
petechiae the thing to be proved then
the second sentence is called hey - the
second sentence is Hey - Hey - means
cause cause what is the cause do MOT
because of seeing fire because there is
smoke and why is this a cause it says
yet rated room at reactor one knee he
that Reza tread whom aha
wherever there is fire there is no where
ever there is smoke there is fire yet
300 rumata treasure-trove only where
ever there is smoke there must be fire
so this is called the up t way up t is a
Sanskrit word if you translate it into
English it becomes even more complicated
it means invariable concomitant
literally it means two things go
together
so if you see one you are sure of the
other if you see smoke you're sure of
the fire not the other way around there
may be fire without smoke so they get
the example of today you might have a
heater for example which is hot but
there's no smoke there but there's smoke
there is fire and then peculiar to
Indian Indian logic they have to give an
example they have to you have to say
where did you see this what what is the
what is an agreed-upon example so they
will say yeah Tama Hana say as we saw in
the kitchen there's smoke fire and smoke
together so this this sentence is called
Buddha Hana how many have we got so far
protego thing to be proved second hey to
the cause third one example Hana and
this is a fourth one which is which need
not concern us too much it's just a
matching it just says as that case fire
and smoke in the kitchen so also this
case fire and smoke on the hill it must
be a similar case otherwise you can't
apply that's the fourth sentence there's
a technical term for that and the last
sentence why I'm saying this is the
conclusion
nigga mana the last sentence is simply a
restatement of the first sentence like
in geometry proofs you do therefore and
QED so therefore there is fire on the
hill nigamananda gimana means conclusion
the conclusion is just the restatement
of the thing to be proved the first
sentence now you have five sentences
first one thing to be proved second one
the reason they're off third one example
fourth one matching the cases and fifth
one is restating the thing to be proof
which is conclusion now three of these
are found here first one particular
thing to be proved second one the reason
and third one the conclusion so all of
this reason I'm giving this little
lesson in Indian logic is I just found
this little noted I don't know when I
wrote it maybe
years back or decades back it just says
it just says one pratigya first-quarter
pratigya second-quarter hey to third
quarter
nigga mana hence no repetition that's
what it says
so actually the three thrice it has been
repeated same thing has been said
neither born nor dies again neither born
nor death and again unborn undying but
the first one is what they want to say
second one is the reason therefore
thereof and therefore conclusion thereof
so that way all of it entirely useless
just that I just found it so I thought
it's interesting to share they had a lot
of time on their hands I think all right
so what does it say first it says the
Atman is not born nor does it die we
have already seen this and then it says
it's not as if having existed at some
time then you died and then you're
reborn again this is what is called
ordinarily you know coming into being
going out of existence and again coming
back into being this is not true of the
Atman of you as pure consciousness and
then a series of adjectives is used
ah-ha-ha-ha jaha means the unborn one so
because it does not it is not born the
Atman is not born with the birth of the
body in the body is born it's not that
you are born you existed before the
coming into being of the body so
therefore you are your name is the at
man's name is Maha jaha means the unborn
one normally when we use the word unborn
in English it means somebody isn't
doesn't exist was never born but here it
means somebody who exists all the time
not does not come into existence by
birth so the body is born but you are
not born along with it you existed the
next word used is nithya ha the
unchanging or eternal
it means here in this case with the
death of the body you do not die with
the death of the body you do not die
Sushma Taha eternally unchanging
literally means undecaying purana the
word piranha in sanskrit it means put up
in other though in she ain't ever fresh
and then it says again na hanyate
hanyamane sarire is not destroyed by the
destruction of the body what's going on
here is the sanskrit lexicographer you
know what that is
dictionary those who compiled lists of
words the Sanskrit lexicographer Aska
who lived I think more than two thousand
years ago so he's compiled one of the
first dictionaries of the world and he
is well known for compiling this set of
six changes
he says worldly things especially our
body it undergoes six-fold changes in
Sanskrit shut with the vicara six four
changes
what are these exchanges change number
one birth
jayati but change two is a bit peculiar
having been born it comes into existence
if you think about it sounds a strange
way of putting it but actually if you
think about it it is quite correct that
which was not there is now there so
that's a change right so it's called
asti jaya t born st comes into existence
word that a grows grows so a baby a kid
a little boy or girl a teenager and
grows then the fourth one is vapor
enormity matures and keeps on changing
in middle age reaches a plateau of
development and then approxiately
degenerates ages it's forty sir goes
downhill
degenerates both body starts decaying
and then finally machete dies destroyed
so these are the six four changes
according to you skir the ancient
lexicographer six four changes you would
expect of a body now what has happened
here is if you look carefully these
terms are used to deny those six changes
of you the Atman so by saying a jaha
unborn it denies that inner denies the
first change but and then Nakia it
denies the the last change death McTeer
means eternal does no time so denies the
last change death then shush whatta the
undecaying it denies the fifth change
decay poor Arnim ever fresh it does not
become it does not grow as such it is
eternally fresh so purana means it
denies the third change that is what
that grows so and it is already said and
in between change that it matures and
remains at a steady state for some time
the last one na hanyate hanyamane sarire
a here a little bit of magic is done
with grammar Shankaracharya the
commentator he says the verb
Hania tahan can also represents change
so it means it's a denial of the the
fourth change that is the plateau it
reaches a certain vapor in Amethi
reaches a certain level of development
and remains there for some time and the
second one that not having existed comes
into existence not being there comes
into existence that has already been
denied by the third quarter that it was
not that he was not there and came into
existence by birth so my point is what
this verse is doing though it looks like
repetition what this verse is doing it
denies the six
all changes coming to the body it denies
those six four changes of the Atman yes
oh okay
in Advaita Vedanta no difference Atman
literally means the self you and Brahman
if you look at the derivation
literally the word bringeth at the root
beans the vast it means the vast now why
use two words if they mean the same
thing
the reason is when you look into
yourself the reality that you discover I
am what I am really which is what we are
talking about that is called admin admin
literally means self the essence and if
you investigate this universe the
reality that you discover the reality of
the vast is called Brahman and the
conclusion of a trait of a dante's both
of them are the same thing
Atman is ramen if you want to know
Advaita Vedanta in one sentence it's
that Atman is Brahman the great maha
vaakya
the profound sentences taught to him I
see that thou art that thou art means
that Brahman thou the Atman you are that
a humdrum has me
I am Brahman even more direct I the
atman and brahman Prag kaanum brahma
this very awareness which you have
correctly understood and appreciated is
none other than the ultimate reality
brahman this awareness means we you what
you find yourself inside what we find
look when we look inside what we find
ourselves to be the Atman that is
actually Brahman and another line from
the mandu Kia I am Atmaram I again more
direct very direct this very self is the
ultimate reality Brahman so atman and
brahman are the same reality this is the
central teaching of the of non-dual
Vedanta and if this is appreciated
understood and realized it's enough to
set you free
spiritual freedom moksha Nirvana
whatever you call it this realization is
enough
why would this set us free from
limitation suffering death I'll give you
a pointer you can mull over it and see
what what it means to you that we are
sentient beings we are awareness there's
no there's no doubt about it right
nobody has any doubt that that you are a
thinking feeling knowing aware being are
you with me yeah this is most important
but if you don't take this first step
next will not make any sense I need to
know that you are we are on the same
page or you look confused what are you
talking about
are you aware and I mean aware in a very
general sense are you thinking feeling
desiring hating loving being are you
aware is there consciousness there yes
one to the problem the human problem put
in its most general and fundamental form
is that this consciousness which we find
ourselves to be is a very limited
consciousness by limitation I mean we
are subject to death we're subject to
old age we're subject to disappointment
we are subject to desiring without
fulfillment we have any number of
limitations this is the problem point
number 2 point 1 I am consciousness
point 2 it's a very limited
dissapointing consciousness are you with
me so far would you agree with me that
this is one way of stating the human
problem hmm no it's like what is he
talking about my problem is the traffic
on the way back from and I'm worried
about Lincoln Tunnel that is limitation
that is limitation that's what I'm
talking about any practical problem in
your life that's limitation so that's
the second thing what solution add right
away done to provide series when you say
Atman is brahman you know what they are
trying to say this very consciousness
that we know ourselves to be you know
yourself to be this
is unlimited consciousness this
consciousness is not subject to the
limitations we think it is subject to
and to educate us into our the nature
the real nature of ourselves that's what
our the weight of a round is doing I'll
repeat three points freedom and
enlightenment in three points one is we
are conscious beings we are conscious
second it's a very limited dissapointing
consciousness third we are wrong it's
not a limited dissapointing
consciousness it's actually infinite
unlimited consciousness there is no
problem at all
that's what advaitha with Anto wants to
show us that's the meaning of Atman is
Brahman you don't seem convinced then
you have to keep coming to the class
that's what krishna is telling arjuna
continuously all these things what did
he say you the conscious being arjuna
you don't die first thing he said you
are the only reality the entire universe
is an appearance in you second thing
Atma septem jagat mithya third thing you
pervade everything that you experience
you are not a tiny spark of Chinese Park
of consciousness in a vast uncaring
universe rather the entire universe that
you experience is within you the expiry
even in the language that I'm using if
you notice carefully entire universe
which you experience you pervade it all
you are the vast you are not tiny number
four what was number four the Atman is
it's not an object it's not an object a
premiere it's not an object of knowledge
and that has many ramifications and so
on it's not a doer not an excessive
error and now it is saying this
twentieth verse is saying the Atman is
not subject to the 6 fold changes which
the body is subject to that's what it
just said if somebody say I mean you're
too polite to say it but somebody might
object that these adjectives you are
just fitting them into the 6 fold
changes that you charge what the purana
how do you know that it is denying the
second
the third change something like that
well you take your complaints to Shankar
Acharya I've got the interpretation from
Shankar's commentary on the
bhagavad-gita all right having said this
21st verse Veda Venus enum nityam may
diminish enum neaten uranium europium
uranium ahjumma 'i'm Katims Purusha part
cotton sir Purusha part come got dirty
hunty come come hard dirty hunty come
whom o Partha can that person who knows
the self Atman to be imperishable
constant worthless and immutable slay or
cause to be slain and how so this is the
verse remember the language of slaying
and cause to be slaying is because the
context is the battlefield it basically
means action how can this pure
unchanging consciousness be a doer of
actions how can it be an agent of action
that's what he's asking it starts with a
word Veda no this very important what is
the method of Advaita Vedanta what are
we supposed to do whether here means to
know to realize the whole point of
spirituality according to Vedanta is to
realize realize the teaching as against
what are you supposed to believe are you
supposed to meditate or pray or go on
pilgrimages or subscribe to a particular
faith or church did what we normally
associate with religion what we Dantas
is is all of those may be useful and
helpful but that's not the
the point is use all of that to realize
this truth as Swami Vivekananda said
each soul is potentially divine and the
goal is to manifest this divinity
already within us do it by meditation do
it by service do it by love do it by
knowledge in fact he said do it by
philosophy do it by philosophy by one or
more or all of these and be free so that
is the purpose of religion and then he
goes on to say books temples doctrines
and churches are secondary details so
this realization which sets you free
this is this is the whole purpose of
Vedanta and I dare say of all
spirituality everywhere Bible says know
the truth and the truth shall set you
free basically this thing realization
notice I am making a slight distinction
between knowledge and realization it's
not just knowing it because you can
claim now I know it now I know it
attended the class I read the book I
even memorized the verse I downloaded
the talk so now I know it I spent
countless hours on YouTube so now I know
it so am I free am i enlightened know
what remains is this knowing while
important has to be deepened into
realization which is first-person
experience I must be honestly able to
claim not that the Atman is immortal
Atman is real the Atman is all-pervading
know I am immortal
I am the reality of which the universe
is an appearance I must be honestly able
to claim this to see this not claim it
just as a slogan but actually to see it
so there the knowledge has been
assimilated into realization Swami
Vivekananda says you know tell yourself
again and again that I am that I am that
Atman till that distinct tingles with
every drop of your blood
until it becomes a living reality it's
not brainwashing it is something that
you have understood it must be converted
into a living reality just as we without
any doubt saying that we are bodies
right now at that time we without any
doubt we will see ourselves as an
unlimited immortal consciousness the
spirit not the body so that is
realization and that can be done the
Vedanta process is Shravana monana
needed the asana you listen to this
study it step1 step2 flink it through
every possible doubt yet one has to stay
with it for some time and see what
doubts come up I have seen within
long-standing students questions begin
to crop up the answers to which has been
given of every other class we give the
answers actually but it strike the
question first comes after a long time
then only the answer makes sense that is
the process of mononym in fact there's a
deeper process of mononym that is
reflection when you try to live your
life according to what you have studied
where you try to live your life
according to what you have studied in
that process they'll be struggle and in
that struggle that is basically
spiritual practice things fall into
place when you stay with that insight
this is called the third stage
meditation needed the asana that leads
to the moment of awakening where you see
it is so it has always been so that I am
this unlimited consciousness so this all
this is meant by the word Veda realized
here yourself as this it's already there
you are already this you have hypnotized
yourself into bill we have hypnotized
ourselves into believing that we are
these little bodies that he cages of
flesh and bone swami vivekananda again
and again he would say if only you knew
yourselves as you are as you really are
what would happen if that happen you
ourselves as we really are all our
problems would be solved not that at the
physic
at the practical level if you become
enlightened would it solve the problem
of getting a ticket on your car in the
wrong parking no you'd still have to pay
the ticket but the deepest problem this
problem of very human existence that is
solved you know yourself as beyond all
problems
Wei de you realize yourself as what
again a series of adjectives is given
Avinashi naam indestructible nityam
eternal rajim unborn obvi I'm undecaying
you see again those changes are negated
here if you are Avinashi you are not
subject to death if you are NIT clear
here it means undecaying you're not
subject to v modification old agent
decay if you are Adam unborn clearly you
not subject to the modification called
birth obviou you are not subject to the
modification called growth or
development you are you are one
unchanging such solution such a
consciousness how can such a
consciousness engage in action or reap
the results of action it leads to the
question then who engages in action
it is this consciousness along this
nobody else who engages in action it's
this consciousness alone forgetting its
true nature identifying with body and
mind becomes the Jeeva the sentient
being who engages in action and suffers
the results of action are you all right
so far yes right so he will keep he'll
come back to the same conclusion again
so if you're not the doer the action
will continue at the level of body and
mind everything will continue as the
world continued it's not that when what
you have to realize is even though
acting through body and mind you are
truly
untouched non-acting consciousness right
that is what is to be realized he is not
telling you that's what Arjuna wanted to
do you know he wanted to give up all
this and go away to the mountains and
meditate and be a mendicant a beggar he
says no that's not the way that is also
being trapped in action he will tell
later on giving up action is not
attaining to the state of the non doing
consciousness the non doing
consciousness is always there even in
the midst of intense action the most
intense action can go on and you realize
you are not you are the consciousness
which does not do anything many examples
can be there
imagine a screen on which movie is being
played in the movie intense action is
going on it could be a adventure or
something like that you know there could
be storms or a fire or something
tremendous action is going on yet from
the point of view of the screen nothing
is happening
another example imagine your dreams you
recall your dreams imagine a dream which
was a really happening kind of dream
lots of things happened yet you can
claim with absolute honesty when you
wake up what can you claim nothing
happened nothing really happened because
that was not actually from the point of
view of the Waker none of those things
happen in the dream it did happen but
when you wake up from out of it you
realize it didn't happen analogously can
you imagine yourself to be that light in
which all of these things appear work
out play out and disappear back again
from the point of the other lights
nothing has happened yeah to Brahman it
does not matter from the front from
Ramon's point of view from the point of
view of pure being it really does not
matter it matters from society's point
of view it matters at this level you
know all these non dual teachings they
talk about two truths an absolute truth
and an apparent truth apparent with our
transactional truth so for example right
now we are sitting here and and studying
Vedanta
what level is this zapper in truth
transactional truth it's called wave aha
Rica transactional truth and at the
level of transactional truth all of it
works
there is causality there is karma there
is good there is evil there are things
to be done things can get better things
can get worse and the solution proposed
by a great of a Dante's identify
yourself with the absolute and act in
the relative you cannot not act in the
relative what will you do with this body
and mind even when you realize that you
are Brahman what will you do
right now what you are doing is I do not
know myself as that infinite awareness I
know myself as a very limited conscious
being and I'm trying to do the best I
can
this is our life right now what they are
proposing is if you investigate we will
show you how you are that unlimited
awareness not affected by birth and
death not affected by the vicissitudes
of life and yet you're in the midst of
life now that's a very enjoyable
position and be able position also when
you know you are perfectly safe then you
can play the game to the hilt in fact
then an ethical moral life becomes
possible what have you got to be afraid
of what can tempt you what can what can
scare you nothing the consequences of
that you're asking about why should one
act then the consequences of that one
good way of understanding is if you look
at people you consider to be enlightened
what did they do with their lives and
you will get a wide arranged array of
answers if you look at Ramon marshy he
sat in a cave though he his very
presence was a blessing there have been
enlightened people whom nobody is known
about they have disappeared from society
without people knowing about them on the
other hand they have been enlightened
people who led lives of tremendous
activity and whose blessings we are
counting now the great teachers of
religion the great leaders of social
reform many of them
spiritual masters and they readily
sacrifice their lives because they found
something that was eternal for them it
did not matter this little life they
found an oneness with everything so our
suffering became their suffering and
they wanted to help us out of it
therefore he says therefore fight
therefore do your duty knowing the
reality of yourself to be this now do
you do thou your duty in Arjuna's case
it was fighting the good fight in in our
case we have our little battlefields
each of us does that address your
question ya realize yourself to be this
Center yourself in this realization then
act you say why act at the level of the
body mind what else can you do yes
yes moral ethical life to the to the
best best level that is possible yes
that's perfectly all right yes right
true and this is our this is your
speaking so this is our experience you
would feel that this is how it's going
to be at the beginning it may seem to be
like that but very soon you will see it
is not so because somewhere deep inside
is a feeling that I am this being and
I'm trying to get hold of a theoretical
absolute so I keep slipping back into
what I am very soon it will change into
I am the absolute I keep slipping back
into habitual patterns of activity
habitual thought patterns very soon you
will see all our slipping our mistakes
are because of past conditioning it will
be a very interesting but a very
difficult phase where what will happen
is you are clear about this that I am
the unchanging consciousness no longer
theory you see this is this has to be
the truth and yet in life there is a
struggle and the struggle you will see
is not because somehow I become the body
mind no you will see at even when I
think and the body mind and act
accordingly even then I am NOT the body
mind but I am acting due to strong past
conditioning that deconditioning process
takes time but before that what weight
on to say is that breakthrough is
essential what Vedanta tries to do is
the break
see there are two ways to it one is the
way of conventional the way the
conventional spiritual way is lot of
spiritual practice yes you are the body
mind you are this person not try to be
an unselfish person try to be a truthful
person try to be a disciplined person
try to meditate twice a day pray thrice
a day or whatever have devotion do good
to others so all these spiritual
practices they continue as what what are
you I am this person
what are these spiritual practices doing
from the point of view of Ananta they
are preparing you from this insight but
a time will come when through these
conventional spiritual practices one
makes a breakthrough and you have that
insight clearly suddenly there is a
shift and the reference of the I when I
say I it refers to body mind it changes
it refers to that witness consciousness
that unlimited consciousness we are
talking about you see it must be so once
it has changed then those practices will
still continue you're still not a fully
enlightened being those practices will
still continue but they are more like
expressions of the truth what you have
found yourself to be you see this is the
wise way of living no longer to find
this truth you found it already now to
establish yourself in that truth you
will see to act contrary to ethics to
act contrary to spiritual practices will
will seem contrary to what you have
found you found yourself to the will to
be the witness consciousness immortal
the only reality and to act out of
impulse out of anger or out of hatred
will seem very contrary to what your
form still you will keep on that
slipping will keep on happening why
because the mind is conditioned but less
and less and less so
this is called the path of Gyana yoga
difficult one but this is also called
the direct path every other path path is
indirect yes
yes yes it is true of course right there
is only one reality according to Advaita
Vedanta one non dual reality do did you
notice in the sixteen twelve it says the
Atman is the truth or is a reality and
the world is an appearance
it means it's a non dual reality that
means there is no other reality not that
there are many at once and floating
around there's only one that one
consciousness in which the universe
appears right are we all one or
different in the thirteenth chapter
Krishna will say you are that
consciousness other than body and mind
how many consciousnesses are there he
says there is only one consciousness
here one immortal consciousness and know
me to be that consciousness means God so
in that one half of our si answers two
questions
how many admins are there or how many
pure consciousness is how many spiritual
realities are there one and the second
question is what is God in all of this
God is that spiritual reality do you see
then you are saying I and God are one
and the same
yes that's what it is saying but I not
as this individual limited being in your
nature as true spiritual nature as the
unlimited consciousness that is what is
God in add weight of Atlanta in that
sense think about it you are actually
experiencing God right now in every
thought in every feeling in every
experience of life the material which
you are experiencing isn't isn't nothing
other than the divine itself only under
the limitation of our ignorance
then the 22nd verse this is another of
those verses which are chanted when
somebody passes away somebody dies very
famous words from the bhagavad-gita it
says that as we go from death from life
to death to other lives it's like
changing a suit of clothes as you give
up old clothes and put on a fresh suit
of clothes exactly like that we give up
give up old bodies decaying bodies dead
bodies and go on to new bodies 22nd
verse on cg nani
attabi ha hasan cg narnia tabhi ha
navona green hearty Naropa Rani
Navona green hearty Naru Pirani Natasha
irani be hygiene on guitar irani be
hygiene on on Jana Sangh yatin Avenida
he and Jana Sangh attina bah needy he
just as a person gives up worn-out
clothes and puts on other new ones even
so does the embodied self give up
decrepit bodies and enter other new ones
so it's a well-known doctrine of the
Gita of Vedanta that we go through many
lights now what is this going through
many lives what exactly happens Krishna
says birth and death are nothing other
than exchanging bodies one body falls
apart and you go on to get another body
so the example he gives is of clothes
clothes are old or torn so you discard
them and buy new clothes Friday sale or
- Black Friday Black Friday's Black
Friday sale so go and buy new ones God
also has a Black Friday sale sometimes
you go and pick up new ones
except that in this case you are doing
it consciously in our in our own lives
it's done by the law of karma we do not
have conscious control over it what lack
bodies we come into when they will end
and what new bodies will get it's all
determined by cause and effect
everything that is happening now is an
effect of which there are causes and
every cause that is set into motion will
give rise to certain effects now a
little bit of basic Vedanta bodies when
you speak about bodies from a Vedanta
k-- perspective there are three bodies
not one you have three body what one
body is this physical one
the public one which the doctor can
check the one which which is sitting on
the chair this one this is called gross
body not that not in the American sense
of gross physical meaning physical
though it can be pretty gross if you
especially if you cut it open and see
what's inside can be pretty gross but
gross body means physical body in
Sanskrit stool a sharira body number one
second body subtle body suksham sharir
it doesn't mean a particularly slim body
it missions it means what you are
experiencing right now if you ask what's
the proof for the subtle body proof for
the gross body your physical body does
no need to ask this question everybody
knows it exists here it is but what is
the proof of the subtle body again the
you eggs
you experience it all the time thoughts
feelings emotions all of that all the
first-person experiences about yourself
the person you experience yourself to be
that's the subtle body see why I call it
a subtle body why not why isn't it a
part of the gross body it is not know
scientists till now has been able to
discover how you know first for a
scientist the physical body ends at the
brain at the neurons that's it how that
translates into a mind
thoughts feelings emotions memories
clearly they're linked but how nobody
knows I mean many of you studying
biology neuroscience philosophy tell me
is that does anybody know no it's an
amazing thing something that we
experience all the time that's our life
what's our life thoughts feelings
emotions desires the way we are
experiencing it inside that's how we
live our lives we do not experience life
as secretions from the kidney and the
linear elliptical movements in the brain
we do not there's no doubt that it's
happening in the body no doubt about it
science has investigated it in great
detail and all the physical systems of
the body definitely enormous amount of
the knowledge we have we experienced
none of it what we experience inside
each of us right now the first person
experience what are technically called
qualia subjective experiences that's
what is called the subtle body there is
good reason to call it a separate body
there by your very observation the two
are of different nature you can clearly
see this physical body and what it feels
like from inside two different things
finca thought 2+2 is 4 or my name is
Swami Sivananda that's a thought and
touch this physical body these are two
different things entirely so subtle body
suksham sharir what is the subtle body
then physical body we know it's made of
hands and feet and legs and we know
organs and organ systems and cells and
so on what's the subtle body what are
the parts of the subtle body Vedanta
says there's a different ways of
classifying there are actually 19 parts
to it 19 parts the five sense organs not
the physical organs they're parts of the
physical body but the powers the
experiences you get of seeing hearing
smelling tasting touching five sense
organs five motor organs and what are
called the five vital functions punch-up
Ram
that makes y plus 5 plus 5 15 and then
for parts of the mind Manabu digit
tankara the mind itself memory the
function of egotism or ego and intellect
so these are the four together nineteen
parts this comprises the subtle body
according to Vedanta the different ways
of classifying some make it 17 the
Buddhists have a different way of
classifying it and so on but it's
they're all Indian philosophies
acknowledge that you are a subtle body
inside a physical body and there is a
third one according to Vedanta third one
only figuratively called a body it's
called the causal body not casual body
causal body the causal body is that
barrier which transforms you the
infinite consciousness Brahman into this
individual being that what could that be
it's just ignorance it's called a gana
ignorance of our real nature it's called
the causal ignorant that itself is taken
as a body it comes as a first covering
or sheath then it's covered over by the
subtle body then it's covered over by
the physical body why am I saying all
this at death it's the physical body
which dies which is discarded like an
old pile of clothes the subtle body
continues subtle body is not born with
birth is not it does not die with death
it curls up into a little seed and then
goes on until it finds another physical
body where it can express itself so
that's the idea you what about you the
Atman you are pure consciousness you
neither come or not go you have
identified Atman is identified itself
with so many causal bodies and subtle
bodies so it becomes millions and
billions of what are called Jeeva
sentient beings and each of these jiva's
gets different physical bodies and lives
out its life does karma gets the result
of karma and the result of karma is
expressed in newer and newer physical
so this is the cosmic game which is
going on actually you are the infinite
consciousness you are none of you are
not the three bodies you are not the
causal body you are not the subtle body
you are not the physical body at death
physical body dies it is exchanged for
new physical bodies they need not be
human the black friday sale lots of
different kinds of bodies are available
we go from life to life means from
physical body to physical body but we go
means what goes the subtle body goes and
the causal body also travels these two
travel together causal body is a
technical point it will not take it you
not concentrate upon it but the subtle
body is something that we all experience
right now we are experiencing it yes ah
this very good question so what is
freedom
what is moksha what is not moksha this
kind of existence is not an option so
death is obviously not an option that is
not freedom because you still exist as a
person and you will go on
so in death you do not die with death
you go on and your existing as a person
it's not good news in from from Vedantic
not only we don't think all Indian
schools it's not good news it's the bad
news actually you don't stop at death we
have existed earlier we'll keep on
existing and as long as you want to as
long as you are having a good time God
says go on have a good time
and you say no I have had enough I want
to go back to my real nature then
spiritual life starts for you you get
the bulletin of the Vedanta Society that
there's a Gita class yes now let me
complete that and answer to that
question so then what happens at moksha
you see these questions and answers they
are not for one person so when one
person is asking a question don't switch
off listen to the question and I listen
to the answer often the answer may be
effective for you and not even for the
person who asked the question is what
happens at moksha then what what are we
aiming for at moksha
the subtle body which has been getting
many many newer and newer bodies
physical bodies that subtle body is also
dissolved it it's also made of nature
physical bodies are made from nature
five elements subtle body is also the
material the very interesting Vedanta
would actually agree with science
Vedanta would say yes even the mind is
material but what is not material is is
the Atman consciousness it's an entirely
different kind of reality so that
remains by itself or you can say more
figuratively the individual being the
sentient being merges back into the
absolute but really there's no merging
back you are the absolute and you
realize yourself at the absolute you
wake up from this dream or sequence of
dreams that's what happens and when that
happens that is called enlightenment but
that subtle body in which the
Enlightenment has happened that will
continue for a little while because of
past Karma then you call that being an
enlightened being so that person becomes
an enlightened master enlightened
teacher and those are the from vedantic
perspective they are the teachers of
religion they are the the great
spiritual masters of humanity yes yes
I'm not including the causal body it
will complicate matters and the causal
body is something that Vedanta talks
about more but the subtle body is easily
understandable so the subtle body will
continue until the the Karma which gave
rise to this particular embodiment until
that is over
the physical body dies remember all our
physical body is not just enlightened
beings all these physical bodies we have
they are produced by our past karma and
so they will live as long as that
particular portion of karma which has
produced this body when that is
exhausted this body will die but lot of
karma is accumulated our balances are
not empty so they will produce newer
carb and new Karma's we have added to it
in this life
well some might retain there are certain
ones who retain their subtle bodies even
after enlightenment it's possible they
are the ones who are called eternally
perfected once they exist the
Bodhisattvas our Sri Ramakrishna's to
talk about neat jacinta's but the
general form of the problem you know
mathematics is the general problem the
problem is this and you get free ones
enlightenment one stays enlightenment at
the death of that enlightened person the
death of the innocent person means death
of the physical body and with that the
dissolution of the subtle body again I'm
not making this up this opener should
speak about it that it says just as the
rivers run into the sea the very poetic
description of the of the passing of an
enlightened one as the rivers run into
the sea and merge and become one with
the sea so also the nineteen parts of
the subtle body of this enlightened one
they run back into the vastness of
nature and become one with it the
enlightened one remains as prominent as
pure consciousness yes all of them are
material yes as material yes right and
if you're interested you can split these
three bodies this again basic Vedanta
you can split or you can analyze these
three bodies into the five sheets we
have often talked about the five sheets
the food the food sheet the physical
body the vital sheet the mind sheet the
intellect sheet and the Bliss sheet in
sanskrit annamaya kosha pranamaya kosha
manomaya kosha vicky annamaya kosha are
in the microtia
can you match them with the three bodies
the food sheet is the physical body
gross body so food sheath annamaya kosha
is the physical body then this subtle
body has three sheets in them
pranamaya manomaya VG anima that's the
subtle body second body the third body
is the causal body that is the
anandamaya kosha so the five sheets as
if there are five coverings to the Atman
you can imagine it that way like nesting
dolls the five coverings to the Atman
you are none of them so in Sanskrit or
in Hindi even Vedanta teachers they say
all of this which I'm saying they would
say it in half a phrase sharee Rattray
of election punch akash of election are
searched on and Artois tum ho maharaj
they will say you sir are the pure
consciousness pure being pure bliss not
the distinguished from the three bodies
distinguished from the five sheets you
are this immortal being yet right now
your existing embodied and that's fun
once you do realize what you are you
have this nice vehicle to drive around
cool vehicle yeah it's not just a suit
of clothes it's a very sophisticated
sort of suit of clothes it can do so
many things many apps it's it's a very
very sophisticated iPhone that you've
got that God has given you all of them
are Maya correct they are all products
of Maya and technically they are all
Brahman is there Eddy this way Brahman
if Brahman is the only reality that
exists then all of these are also
Brahman it's because of Maya it appears
to be not permanent the eternal appears
to be the the changing the pure
consciousness appears to be non
conscious object the debt which is pure
bliss appears to be a life of sorrow and
misery in between is Maya the Veil of
Maya Eliot yes I'll come to you Bill
Elliott put it so beautifully he says
the wasteland I think in between the
intention and the act
the doer and the deed in between the
intention and the act Falls the shadow
hmm but shadow is Maya yes we'll end
with bills question yes you can prove it
in the fake plug in the bits very easily
the question was suppose an enlightened
person is to have a stroke and loses his
or her mind how do you fit it into the
picture now analyze that question the
enlightened person what does the person
think of himself or herself to be pure
awareness pure awareness not having a
brain or nervous system cannot have a
stroke that's number one as awareness
itself you cannot have a stroke what
what would have a stroke there are no
moving parts to have a stroke okay
the brain can have a stroke it can and
as a result lose its functionality the
beauty of Advaita Vedanta is it does not
contradict science in any aspect
neither physics nor medical science
those areas are left untouched what
medical science says about the brain and
the body that accepts exactly what will
happen if there is a stroke in the body
but internally the person is aware in
fact I can tell you an actual example
Swami Ranganath Ananda ji who was the 13
president of the order I have heard from
his say work with his assistant young
monk that when maharaj
towards the end of his life he suffered
from the stroke which left him partially
paralyzed the datum the moment he
suffered from that stroke that young
Swami he told me that it's very clear
for us he was sitting there in the room
remember this is 95 year old monk he
looks at me and he says call the doctor
something is happening in my brain and
so they call the doctor and then the
stroke happened and a part of the body
was paralyzed and they had to go to
physically they were able to save him
and physiotherapy only regained most of
the act only still there was a tremor in
the hand and all of that
and all it did was it increased his
curiosity about the brain and he read
books about the brain and he would later
explain it to you in great detail what
exactly happens in the brain when there
is a stroke what about you Swami oh I'm
fine
Swami Siobhan and the Dai disciple of
sri ramakrishna when he was very ill he
also had a stroke and he was partially
paralyzed when people came to meet him
in bellybutton the main minister he was
the president of the order swami we
heard how are you feeling now he said oh
I'm fine no Swami we heard about this oh
you mean the body oh it's not that all
good it's very bad it's and if they're
not being funny it's and it's not very
difficult either when you make the shift
clearly it's not it's not you don't have
to pretend to be not affected you can
clearly see there is something which is
not at all affected absolutely not
affected and there is something which is
affected and the two are not equally
real that which is not affected Israel
that which is affected you can say it's
a tiny part or it's just an appearance
where Dante would say it's just an
appearance in the non affected reel so
that's a good point to end it on all it
says I'm it's sounds very easy all it
says you to notice it it's there for the
noticing even if you cannot manifest it
in your actions right now even if you
say I slip I fall doesn't matter even if
you just notice it and begin to see it
for what it is the atman yourself that
itself gives a great deal of peace and
freedom tremendous freedom there is
daily you will have a core which will
always know it's all right I pray by the
grace of the Lord that we may all have
this insight in this very life itself Oh
Shawn
the shanti shanti hurry he owned that
sat sri ramakrishna Aparna Musto